all right so here we are in Holiday
Boost number three and we're working our
way through the prepare section as you
can see um we we did install bash uh
last time we did create a GitHub account
and now we're going to use the stuff
necessary to talk to GitHub the the get
the get in GitHub tool um hopefully
we'll we'll I'll show you how to log
into GitHub from the command line which
is really cool uh we're going to create
our first dot files and then we're going
to individually go through the setup of
all these different things hopefully
we'll get pretty far along here but uh
and then we'll get down to learning to
code down
below uh I think we're probably going to
spend the most time on bin Basics
that'll probably be in the next video um
so let's get to it install git and the
GitHub Tool uh the get and GitHub
command line tool provide enhanced
Enchanted Oracle of GitHub realm uh
empowering Cod Mage to summon interact
with and manage repor repositories a
repository is a weird word but it just
means a place to put things uh directly
from the terminal with getting GitHub
you don't just push code you create you
weave github's collaborative magic into
your workflow creating PO requests
reviewing code and managing issues as
evly as casting a spill it Bridges a gap
between your local workspace and
expansive GitHub Cosmos giving you power
to man manage repositories explore
contribute archives and orchestrate
contributions without ever breaking your
focus where Cod Mage seeking to unlock
the full potential github's
collaborative incantations GitHub is a
the GitHub tool GH is an indispensable
artifact so here's how you install Ed
it's not hard people people you can do
this in one command all right so let me
show you so we're going to pull up that
terminal again how do you pull up a
terminal on Mac command
space command space type terminal enter
all right Brew let's clear the screen
you can type clear Brew install G and
GitHub all right this will go get
it and it'll update it if I mean if you
do it again you know this mine updated
right because I already had it installed
so that's how you do it on a Mac how do
you do that on
Windows well let's go do it let's go do
windows so here we are on get this is
we're still have the same terminal up
you guys remember how to get the
terminal do you remember how do you get
a terminal on Windows you push the
Windows
key right wait you push the Windows key
and type bash
enter and your terminal will come up
okay don't worry we're going to get a
better terminal later this is the
terminal you can always fall back to
right now what so now we need to install
GitHub and uh and get bash so the
command for that is when get install D-
ID uh uh we already had git we already
had git because we had to spell git Bash
that's so that came with it so now we
need to get the GitHub CLI so GitHub do
CLI and that's the CLI stands for
command line interface that's what we're
using right now and we're going to go
get
that and that'll go download it for you
and do the install you might have to
click on some things to say hey I'm an
admin or whatever uh it goes without
saying that you need admin we talked
about it in the two days ago but or two
two sessions
ago um so you can click on
okay uh and there you go you should you
should have it you should be able to say
gh-- version
and there it is so you're you're ready
to do the next thing you can leave your
terminal up because we're going to do
something right away after this so let's
go back to Mac um and do that
confirmation as
well um
wait what did I just
do what did I do Rob here we go all
right yeah okay so we got Brew install
we did the windows
thing and on Linux it's just pseudo app
get get install so so this is a root
command I'm going to do this on Linux if
you if you already have Linux you
already know how to do this probably but
it's worth showing you so I'm actually
going to use I'm going to log into Anon
which is my Linux machine so I know it
looks like I'm on Windows but now I'm on
a Linux machine and so sudu apt we
haven't learned SSH we will uh in
terminal velocity not in this book so
sudu apt
install um uh get and uh GI Hub dasc
life and type my password for
this did I spell it wrong what did I
what did I what did I do wrong there
what did I do
wrong oh it's GH is it actually GH I
don't think it
is I thought it is it GH I mean I put I
put in the book I hope it's true yep
that's it it says the following packages
will be upgraded yes please
all right so that that has to be done as
root I don't know why it pops up all
this stuff every time this is this is
Linux one2 one2 uh server by the way if
you don't know so that that was a Linux
machine let's go back to Windows now
we're on Windows all right so we we that
was fast right I told you this wasn't
going to take that long um in fact most
of these prepare steps besides the
learning part is is are pretty quick
once you get the package managers
installed brew and wiget which comes
with the windows um so let's go
back so there you go we've got we've got
that that step was pretty quick right
now let's actually use it to do
something rather than talk about it
right we're not going to talk about it
we're going to use it and you're going
to incrementally use it that's how I do
everything you're going to incrementally
learn the things as you're using them if
you ever want a deep dive obviously you
can do that but I'm not going to
overwhelm you with everything all up
front so uh so let's go ahead and log in
GitHub now there are lots of ways to do
this but this is by far the easiest for
a beginner okay um you can go to GitHub
and you can do the tokens and everything
but there are a lot of veterans right
now and I'm if you're a veteran and you
don't mind admitting it I would really
love you to raise your hand you're not
going to be in the video but I'd really
love you to raise your hand and tell me
you did not know that you could do this
from the GitHub command line tool there
are people that are still doing the old
steps necessary to authenticate to
GitHub and I got to tell you it's a pain
it is really painful to watch um and I
also want to say that this is one of the
reasons that we're using getback
and that we're using uh you know brew
and a Mac and and you know desktop Linux
as opposed to logging to a server using
a container or using a virtual machine
if you know what that is because what
we're about to do doesn't work if you're
doing those things it works better for a
beginner here let me show you so let's
do this so how do I log in and um so you
didn't know about it before you watched
okay so let's do this let's say so let's
go back to our terminal and and we're
going to do um GH off login okay now
this is going to ask what you want is
GitHub or whatever you can use GitHub um
and by the way if you're if you're in
the Enterprise you can say Enterprise at
that point we're going to say
https and um authenticate with get Hub G
credentials yes now I I have to be
careful here because as soon as I say
yes here it's going to show me a a
shortlived token that I you know if you
watching this you would it would it
would you know it would not be good
right uh so I actually can't show you
these steps I I thought about creating a
a fake account for this and I'm not
going to do that so just say yes to this
and I'm going to say no and then when it
says login with a a web browser uh you
say yes and it what it will do is it
will give you a code that you can copy
and paste and then it will you hit enter
after that and it will open up your web
browser and this works on everything
this works on Linux desktop this works
on Mac this works on windows with with G
bash and it will open up your web
browser to a page and then you just you
log into GitHub you know and and you and
you tap and you say yes I want to do the
thing and you paste in your code and
then it will say you have been
authenticated okay now if you need to
escape that for any reason control C
right I just control C to interrupt and
I realize now that we need to add that
to the book so actually let me add
um Let me let me let me let me uh
quickly I need to I need to add
something to the to the book here issue
I'm just going to go ahead and add an
issue uh I'm going to add a quick bug
and say um add controls
C earlier in book for breaking out of
password prompts Etc so I need to add
that to the book I'm going to go ahead
and add that I I don't know if you can
tell but this this thing that I just did
is is I'm it's actually um I'm using the
GitHub tool for
this and you're going to be getting good
with this too but see this is what I'm
doing I'm using the GitHub tool to
create that issue so now this I'm this
is not part of the book but so as you
can see you see how I'm listing all the
issues on it everything all through the
GitHub tool and I've got scripts and
stuff to make it easier all covered in
terminal velocity but that's why you're
using it one of the Reon you're using it
that's a very real example of of um of
you know that that usage so let's let me
go ahead and open up uh the the document
again um and let go back to coade for
Spellbook and I'm doing terminal based
browsing this is a web browser in the
terminal it's called links and w3m
they're both really great also cover
covered in terminal velocity we are not
covering that now stay tuned that'll be
in the next book um or you can just
watch me uh when we're not doing book
stuff so um anyway is still get in the
GitHub tool log into GitHub so log into
GitHub um so when wielding the tools of
GitHub of the code Mage having access uh
to get up is essential for managing
repositories collaborating with others
and coning spells uh they get up GH tool
as a powerful artifact in your magical
Arsenal I just showed you some of the
Spells and Magic you can do uh with it
but this is the one you need to start
with GH off login once you do that on
this computer you won't have to do it
again probably for a year
um so and after that all your GitHub
commands Will Will just work okay so uh
pause the video right now and spend some
time making sure you get this to work um
how long it's been since you used the
get authentication right um yeah if you
either use the UI or whatever right but
using the GitHub command line tool is so
easy to authenticate now I don't even
know where the tokens and everything are
being written I don't care and and I do
this at work all the time when I need to
log in on a Mach
uh but knowing the step GH off login is
really valuable and having the GitHub
command line tool early in your you know
tool set when you're setting it up is
going to make everything easier later on
I'm going to prove it to you and I
promise you nobody is teaching this this
isn't going to get taught to you in like
the MIT lost semester or anything
nobody's teaching you this they should
be because it's so easy uh okay Game
Changer one has made me setting up a
computer right you just found about this
recently good well now everybody's
watching this knows about it now and
reading the book um and and so so here
we see I mean if you just a little side
note if you have gone through the other
process of trying to get authenticated
and set up all the tokens with SSH and
everything on Gib so that your terminal
works you know the pain that we're
talking about and this has all been
masked by one command GH off login learn
it love it tell your friends about it
they'll love you for it um all right so
select get up account select prefer
protocol uh type enter type enter to
accept the login web web browser copy or
remember a onetime code and press enter
your web browser should open
automatically if your browser do not
open you can always go to this URL by
the way this is the one reason we use
bash on the computer and not something
else like a virtual machine that would
have not be able to open your web
browser um click continue paste the
onetime code review the permissions
follow the remaining authentication
steps uh and when the process is
complete the C will confirm it by saying
you are logged in as blah so um to
ensure your login worked uh try the
following commands let's actually do
that now and this by the way this goes
for Windows or Mac so I don't have to do
it on both systems you can just imply
that so so now um and and by the way I
don't have to do it in my other junky
terminal because I'm using Western but
it's the same thing we're going to
install westerm next coming up so uh so
you know stay with me here um let's do
this let's make um what am I doing where
are you are you guys there still
something is not right all right okay
here we go so uh so I'm using I'm using
t-o to go back and forth you will learn
that but not in this book you're going
to learn that in terminal velocity in
terminal velocity use how to use use t-o
to go back and forth between multiple
windows and cut and paste and all that
stuff that stuff is not covered in this
book and in the holiday boost terminal
velocity we're going to cover all that
um GH off status okay so let's go do
that so GH o
status uh so there it is and there's my
token uh it tells me I've been logged in
and what my permissions are um the only
other thing I've ever had to do is I've
had to add permissions to delete repos
um but that's not an issue for you right
now right now you're just going to be
making new ones so what is the other
command GH repo list GH repo list now
you're not going to have any repos
obviously I've got several several pages
of them so if I yeah if I if I this is
like I have tons of repos and by the way
this shows you all the repos even those
that have been archived that your your
organization has access to and
everything so you know that that's
that's you probably say you don't have
any repos yet so let's make one watch
how easy this is oh my gosh I am so
happy that we have this possibility for
beginners now um so create your first
dot
files all right let's talk about what
dot files are uh dot files are
configuration files control how your
tools your terminal and your environment
work uh they're named because of the
leading dot you know like bcbc westerm
even though a lot of people would say
what about xtg config home yeah well
there's a lot of you know xtg Nazis out
there they tell you that you need to put
everything in xtg appropriate places and
for right now we don't care we're just
putting them where the applications
developers decided is the place to put
them Vim RC Wester Lua and Bach C which
begin with
dots you know don't Kill the Messenger
I'm just telling you so um despite
they're assuming a so files that begin
with DOT by the way uh TFA on GitHub
earlier which showed how to set up tofa
on GitHub um I did I haven't got any
segments on how to set up tofa that is
up to you if you want to set that up
somebody asked about TFA on GitHub um I
do have TFA and and I use I use a UB key
which is conveniently stored with my
teeth
so I don't lose it and I use the UB key
I you can set up UB key that's what I
suggest if you want to that's a terminal
velocity topic um we are not going to
talk about anything else there all right
get up force me to set up it was a
little painful did they but now it's
working get up force you to go through
the tofa thing
H I'm sorry about that so I guess that's
something we probably want to put in the
book somehow right how to how to set up
the tofa you get two UB Keys is this I I
think two identical UB Keys is the
safest I don't have that right now but
um setting up toffa is not fun uh I I
the reason I'm not going to put it in
the book is because and the the steps
that I had there were pretty generic is
because they change it all the time they
do they're they're constantly changing
it how to L in so so make sure you do
that uh I hate GF since they forc me to
TFA did they they just force you to do
to aay as well that's interesting okay I
need to make a note about that um issue
uh whoops
issue let's see
document um add something
about uh to fa to the GitHub login
section I'm just going to put a quick
little thing
here
add about to
fa do the GitHub login
section how much time we
got okay 17 minutes or
so and okay
so enter the body
submit so I've got some issues on here
so there we go I'll go ahead and and
edit that a little bit later um thank
you for that
though they forced everyone a few days
ago seriously this is why we do a boost
every year this is why the book is
perpetually unpublished or unfinished
because there's constant changes they're
now forcing it you resurrected an old GI
up account and they wouldn't let me
access until I set to a pay really what
wow that I'm glad you guys are here to
do this live I'm G to this is another
reason for me to cycle through it every
time right I you just use SMS at first
it worked okay but I had to run and get
my phone every time yeah I hate that I I
mean I think that's going to in the book
is I I think TFA with SMS is the easiest
for most beginners but I think getting
an authentication tool at some point
covering TFA is unfortunately not
something that's covered by any
educational institution on the planet
Earth but everybody's required to know
how to use
it and so I don't know where that goes I
I feel like that does kind of since it's
kind of a blocker here we got to have to
talk about it if it's your very first
coding experience your first technical
experience I've been making a habit of
not covering things that are not
required but you guys have just proven
to me that it is required so I will add
a section a tiny section about tofa
there um hopefully the kids have phones
right so you know it's funny you said
that because I got rid do I still have
the phone
thing I think I
do I think who what you need I think I
had you have to have a
phone um what it takes
wait learn the code oh no it's in uh
prerequisites it's in prerequisites
now you need a computer and a keyboard
you need a phone uh for research and
reading while working okay so there is
there is a note about here I'm going to
add this um I'm going to add a comment
to the issue uh to do that so you guys
thank you for your feedback this has
been really helpful um uh add it to
justification
for uh phone in
prerequisits under front all right so
I'm just putting a comment there to make
sure I look at it so guys now you see
this just so you can see all the stuff
that I'm doing is all using the GH tool
everything you're seeing me doing right
now is from the command line is all the
GH tool um and if I had to do this with
the web interface it would have taken me
five times as long if not more
so I I just I I constantly want you to
see the very real benefit of having the
GH tool on your system uh there's an
effort called wi off yes there's the
whole the whole two 2fa thing is is is
the whole conversation and I need to uh
boil it down into my Baseline
recommendation for most people um
there's yeah there's there's the windoff
tool which I use the windows
authenticator for work Microsoft
authenticator there's there's a number
of others uh there's the one from AI
there's AI which is really great the
problem with having a tool like that is
that if your phone dies you're you're
done so you know you have to weigh that
against having a a backup method of
logging in I've been locked out on my my
email before because my I my phone died
and I had no other way and I had to like
access them and call the people and
everything so so having a conversation
about um uh tofa is um is is important
right uh yeah cloudbased authentication
so we need to do tofa uh conversation um
unfortunately that's going to have to
happen under the under the log GitHub so
um hopefully everybody's logged in
GitHub at this point um because
everything else we're going to assume
you are we're getting into the real fun
stuff though so we're going to go play
around with the dot files we're going to
install westerm and all of that you can
use TP yep yep keep XT that's my
favorite I use kead XC all the time uh I
have lost my keypad XA data file um I've
actually embedded my kead XC encrypted
data file in a picture before and stored
it in a public space uh there's a lot of
really fun things you can do there when
it comes to
authentication um but those are all
terminal velocity things so for you
right now you just need to set up the
minimum amount of of SMS on your
phone I I can tell you right now if
you're watching this and you're your
first timer and you're new to Tech the
the thing to do is to use SMS on your
phone with UFA and be done with it that
is all you need to do for now all this
conversation about the best way to
manage your password security and
everything that's a terminal velocity or
a knowledge Warrior conversation um it's
you know autodidactic not knowledge
Warrior kind of thing how to manage your
passwords how to manage your logins
those are topics for a different book
okay so right now you're totally fine to
just use you know SMS messaging as your
backup to log in and and that's totally
okay okay so um uh and and let's just
let's let's go on from that okay so um
there are uh at this moment you can
actually create a repo um we are
actually going to create the first repo
we're going to create is the do files
repo uh we are not going to create a
profile repo we're going to direct that
at terminal velocity um and if you just
created a get account called K plus nice
nice that is a great name by the way
that is a great name I like your name
you came up with um it's just so easy to
remember I'm E I already remember it so
uh and probably all configure their GI
up accounts with their teacher cell
phone number pass it around when a sign
to receive codes of SMS yes they can do
that but I also really strongly opposed
to people becoming dependent on a
teacher for anything so if that's the
only thing a teacher wants to offer
that's fine uh most teachers will not be
giving their kids uh access because
access is I know this book is designed
for 12-year-old but technically you need
to be
13 um in fact I've just decided to make
my target audience
13 I've did I'm going to change that in
the book because it's illegal
technically it's illegal for anyone
under 13 be on get him it's against the
terms of service so I I need to make
another issue for that so uh bug um
change age of Target to
13 legal uh age for
GitHub and I I probably you know
somebody's somebody's gonna somebody's
going to come at me and they gonna be
like dude you're telling people to like
break the terms of
service it's another thing about doing
private mentoring that's different than
I mean
I I'm not going to say anything
else I'm not going to incriminate myself
any
further uh
so your display
name yeah that I love that name it is a
great name and it's easy to say capelas
yeah you could change your Twitch name
to that
too so anyway um got to remember when
you pick a username other people going
to be using your username a lot and so
the shorter and more memorable the
better whether it's chat forums or they
want to you know pin you in a in a in an
issue so that you know you get notified
it's really important that you have
small names you know memorable names all
right so um I'm going to change the
official age to um to 13 um create your
first dot files um okay this is actually
really fun and I'm just going to say I
am so proud of how much time I SP on
this and how easy it is having gone
through all the other Alternatives so I
obsess about trying to make things as
easy as possible for you as a beginner
and yet still have it be real and I am
so encouraged by this okay so do files
are configuration we talked about what
they are how do you get them right so
this has got to be one of the biggest
problems to get any beginner started and
I'm going to tell you my story about
what I did and then I'm going to tell
you what we're going to do and how much
easier it is okay so since the dawn of
Unix Unix administrators you know the
knowledgeable Wizards and mentors out
there have been and mages of different
kinds they have been sharing their
knowledge with a very select group of
apprentices and they have been saying
this is how you do it and part of that
apprenticeship is sharing with you if
you're lucky you know their dot files
and there was no way to share code back
then I know this is a boomer thing to
say but in my day back in the day it was
like you'd have to ask somebody You' say
you know pre- internet even I mean there
was an internet but it was only barely
out you know and people didn't put their
dot files on on the internet a lot there
was no place to share them so you were
really lucky if you could get a you know
a knowledgeable veteran to share with
you their bash RC or their Vim RC or
their configuration file and as a
beginner you're already scared because
you're like I don't even know how if I
can use whim let alone you know the
natural whim that it comes with and so
you know you're you're left with this in
this Lurch you're like I don't even know
how to get started and this has got to
be the single biggest barrier to entry
for people that want to get into Tech
and people that want to get into into
Linux and stuff like that and Unix has
been this barrier and it's been tribal
knowledge for decades for decades this
has been tribal knowledge and one of the
great things about GitHub is that tribal
knowledge is now everywhere there are
literally tens of thousands of dot files
that you can go look at on GitHub now
and get ideas from for free you just go
out there and you can share them and you
can say you can you have a chat about
them you can help people you can open an
issue on it if it's got a bug in it you
can suggest something you can learn from
them you can alter yours it's just
absolutely an amazing time to be alive
because when we were growing up no it
was like you you got maybe you're lucky
you get a Unix wizard to email you
theirs otherwise you just had to learn
it and it was a right of passage it was
a right of passage it was a right of
passage it was like oh you know and
sometimes you get Bastard operators from
hell that was a thing bfh and they
wouldn't tell you anything I was like I
don't know about you a lot of times you
were on a multi-user system back then
though so if as long as they kept their
home directories you know open on a
university system or something you could
look at other people's and you would
share them and just copy them over on
the same machine that you were logged
into as if you all were on there so the
point is that we live in a time where
the sharing of these dot files is really
amazing uh and and even the copying of
those dot files has been re made to be
really easy so easy we're going to do it
in one step I I'm so proud of this so
but so you want what we want to do now
is we want to create we want to join the
do files Community we're going to create
you are going to create a your first dot
files repo now I suggest you name it dot
just because it's easier to find and
it's just easier to manage and and and
they can still find it because they put
dot files in your name name or read me
or something if you want to call it dot
files you can but this these
instructions assume the name dot for
your dot files okay and what we're going
to do is we're going to actually reuse a
and this this this part of the book just
talks about everything I told you um so
what we're going to do is we're going to
use this really powerful GitHub command
line tool to do the same thing that you
could do through the guey and you could
click on a bunch of things and put
whatever you want that yeah there are a
lot of people who like do files and then
there's the dot gang and then there's
the do files gang you decide but this is
using dot right and it says here dot is
the name of the repo we created do files
so here is the command now let me tell
you what the command does before we do
it this command this single command
creates a copy a new clone it's actually
not a clone it's how do I put this it's
what it does is it adds to your GitHub
account a repo named dot right so it
adds a repo named
dot that has uh been copied from this
template RBX rob. template and then it
clones it to your local computer and
sets it to private so that people don't
see it yet now you you can change this
later to public once you're more
comfortable with people seeing your dot
files and you have more to show off and
it's I suggest you do that eventually
but for right now you don't really need
to have everybody knowing that it exists
out there um
so okay
so so let's go let's go let's go ahead
and actually enter this command and and
I'm going to do so right here now you
can copy and paste it but in this
particular case I would type it out
you're going to be doing this command a
lot or something like this command a lot
and um so let's go I'm going to go you
you should I'm going to pretend like I'm
you so I'm in according to this um book
we're assuming that you're in your home
directory and you don't know what a home
directory is I talk about this later but
just type PWD and it'll show you where
your home directory is now in terminal
velocity we talk about how to organize
your directory and make it all pretty
and everything but in code Mage we don't
care we're just going to do it right
here okay we can reorganize everything
later so the first thing we're going to
do is this we're going to clone it so GH
create oh sorry repo create and we want
to what are we going to call it let's
call mine uh do files okay and
um and then what I'm going to call it
dot dot okay and then we say okay well
and the order doesn't matter for the
rest of this right so we want to make a
copy from the template RBX Rob SL and
just trust me for now right just copy
this template if again this is going to
create a new DOT files that you own this
doesn't mean you depend on my DOT files
this is just giving you a starter that
creates it for you that then you have
full control of over right this is not
having you're not you're not you know
tied to my DOT file you can go in there
and change them anytime you want so uh
dot template and then um by the way if
you're a veteran and you know what's
going on some of these commands are
destructive so you probably already know
that and you don't want to do that in
that case if you're a absolute beginner
you're going to be totally fine this
isn't destructive but the commands later
will be um so so then we're going to say
I want to clone a copy of it that means
bring it down to my computer and then I
want to make it private right so let's
go ahead and and do that now I'm not
going to name mine dot because I already
have a DOT right so I'm going to do dot
two because I already I already have a
DOT and that would you know mess with my
other dot um so let's go ahead and do
that all right so here we go it's going
to go ahead see how it made a repo up on
GitHub and then it clones into two and
now you can actually CD into two
the change directory CD stands for
change directory and it moves into the
directory and then and then it shows you
where your new directory is if you
forget you can type PWD it stands for uh
print working directory or publish or
whatever or pres working or physical
working there's a million depends on who
you ask uh by the way let's there's this
is also in the book but type man PWD if
you want to know what it says it stands
for manual and you want to get out of
here you type Q uh clear to clear the
screen all of these are covered in the
book so um and LS is covered in the book
show what's in here right so you can see
what's in there list um and now you see
there's a bunch of stuff in here well
let's actually look at what that stuff
is so we're going to use our pager a
pager is a thing I'm paraphrasing the
book right here but I pager is a thing
that just Pages through a long file so
you can read it right uh you could use a
command like cat which is also just
going to show you that what's in the
file problem is is that if the file is
bigger than that uh like it would go off
the screen so like if we did cat um in
let's see cat uh bash bash RC by the way
any of this time you want to if if you
if you don't want to type it you can hit
tab to to tab complete bash tab bash RC
Tab and then you can cat that you can
see that goes way off the screen so
we're going to use something called a
pager and you can either use more or
less here uh Less in my case uh more is
less is literally alas more is an older
pager uh that you'll find on pretty much
any uni system ever created but less is
kind of the new hotness and so my more
is alas to less if if your fingers are
young you could probably just learn less
it's actually easier to type more than
than less in my opinion uh so I'm I'm
down with the Alias being there plus if
I on a system that doesn't have less
that has more it still works so you can
decide whether you want to use more or
less there um and um so
so there there you go um you can
see this is uh the bachelor C file you
can page through it get a sense of what
a script looks like um you don't have to
understand this now but just what we're
doing right now is we're just getting a
sense of what's here and showing you how
to kind of just look around so I'm going
to do more here it's just for setup um
and you can see a little bit of a script
there um and you know we're going to be
doing we're going to be putting a bunch
of these things on here but I just
wanted to show you that okay so now you
have a DOT files now if if you're brave
you can just go ahead and run setup and
you're fine what that'll do is that'll
automatically run the setup scripts for
westerm bash t-x and Bim and if you're
in a hurry and you trust me and you just
want to have it on you can just do that
okay right now if you want to skip ahead
you can just do that right now and what
that will do is that will create a
symbolic link that will destructively
replace the configuration files at the
right location for each of these tools
Western bash t-mo and Vim we're only
going to be using Western bash and Vim
and that includes neim uh in this video
I mean in this in this this segment of
the book um but you know it does set it
all up now having said that we're now
going to do each one of those things and
go through them briefly to talk about
what it's doing so you can understand it
and hopefully the goal here is to hit
the middle ground between you just just
trusting me and just running these
things and actually you know
understanding at least generally what
they're doing okay before you do it so
that you can feel confident saying okay
I'm I'm down and this stuff is all
talked about in the book and so after
you've got your dot files replaced uh we
have that this is just a breakdown what
those things are I've already talked
about that uh how computer people like
stupid puns LOL more and less I know
great uh you got a command on found for
what what what did you get a command on
found for for
CD or for
setup I don't know what what come in for
the GH
tool oh
yeah not found setup yeah if you're
trying okay if you're trying to run the
setup command you just need to do do
slash setup but but let's let's wait on
that
[Music]
um wait what oh are you on Windows
unexpected
token I think I think we have a
corrupted
file I do I think we I think we have a
corrupted file on
that yeah I I think that's a corrupt
file because it was made with windows at
one point are you using git bash it's
really important that we know
that so let me let's go do
that
um I'm going to go ahead and and go
check it out on Windows let's go see all
right so let's do the exactly the same
thing here I think I have this here
already
actually um C do temp actually no let's
do well mine I actually the do template
is the actual file it's the same thing
so we'll just do that let me do dot
template and see set up and see what
happens so it's installing the nerd
fonts get bash is is fine doing it I'm
doing it right now so I don't I don't I
don't know what the problem is so we
need to figure out how come you're
having a a problem with
that um because mine's not
uh it might be the way in M well msus
has a problem but not
gash so there's something going on uh
with your particular setup which is why
I want to understand why that's not
working
um it could
be your uh your your
configuration um of your git
repost I I know what the error is I've
gotten them before but I'm it's because
your line endings are
wrong and
um
yeah are you using are you using git
bash or using msus 2 if you're using
msus 2 it won't
work unfortunately I it's just it's just
a file
thing so I know D Unix we're not doing
that I know bash commands doesn't work
for me on Windows I'm asking me to
install a distl do not uninstall WSL
absolutely do not do
that you see Ms 2 and your task manager
that's fine does your windows say menw
64 yeah you're probably using msus msus
has this problem this is why we don't
use it this is why we use G bash instead
of M2 M2 specifically has this problem
and G bash does not I do not know why
but is I I don't
know uh yeah download get for Windows to
get line ending right absolutely it's
annoying look I know I don't like it but
it's the way to
go get bash superiority so what I need
to know is if you
go all right so how did you start this
did you double click it or did you go to
the search bar and type
bash and make sure you're starting get
bash we're setting up get bash on
windows so and we're not going to talk
about why we're going through the book
right
now so if you can join the book it's
pinned in the chat you can go click on
the book if you want to follow along
we're in setting up get I I just really
need to make sure of this so can I I
need to make absolutely sure that you're
running GI bash and not something else
uh
so's it called sets2 I typed in get bash
term bash
setup yeah we're not don't don't don't
search no okay one of the re so
somebody's like trying to figure out how
to debug this on their own and I'm going
to tell you right now if that is you
you're going to be inundated with way
too much information at this point
there's at least 12 different ways to
run bash on Windows and they all have
very strange nuances and I've spent
literally probably dozens of hours at
this point getting you the simplest
possible thing so that you can get to
the point where you're coding and in my
experience when you have G bash
installed um you're not going to get the
errors that some of the people just got
and you won't get other errors that WSL
is going to cause you to have so please
just trust me on this go back and read
the section about just trust me um make
sure that you're using G bash the way
that you'll know get your G bash is a
thing is it will say user user b bash um
or or or or whatever I mean however you
want to see it down here it should say
that you're using get bash in some form
um and it's it's really really important
uh yeah so get for Windows sets the
default get config to commit the uni
style line endings which is auto
configures true so lead I know that's
true but my my the point of it is I want
to make sure that we don't have to do
that I think we might have to do a get
config and that that's uh uh the core to
autocom is true is is I think an extra
step that they need to do so so actually
Dale let's let's let's try this okay
because I think I think that's the
reason it's not working for for you and
if that's true I need to add it to the
book um okay try reinstalling you can
try reinstalling but but I actually
think it might still be a problem I
think it might still be a problem and I
think that LE I was going to talk about
what Le's talking about but I wanted to
see if we do need to still I think I
think here I think the reason that this
is happening is
because because I think the reason no no
I don't have any of those things
set so so this is okay we're going to
take some time this this video is going
to go a little long but we're going to
take some time to figure this out Dale I
I want to stay with you on this one okay
so I want to make sure that you're
installing I saying your name right I
hope so we want to make sure that you're
installing get bash and we want to make
sure that get bash has the same problem
you just had because I know how to fix
it the one of the fixes is to add a
configuration line but if I can avoid
telling people how to do that then I
would like to be able to be sure of that
um if if someone could follow along with
get bash and try
it uh and figure get to never do any
help a magic with that m l is I always
Force un line on Windows there there are
lots of schools that thought on that and
and I don't want to dub tail this entire
this beginner boost into a conversation
about dealing with line endings and get
get up that is a terminal velocity
conversation all I want to get to right
now and and by the way I'm I'm
definitely hearing everybody I I I hear
what you're saying I'm very very aware
of everything you're saying
uh I know about the lineing issue I I'm
live through the age where we had to
take care of Mac line endings as well um
what I'm trying to do right now is
arrive at the absolute simplest solution
for a beginner and as of this moment uh
based on my research um and I want to
make sure that research is correct uh
installing git bash assuming they don't
have anything else on their system and
they haven't messed around with their
git configuration which you can with a
beginner will work it will work I
actually tested it on my system just now
and now
I'm a little worried because somebody
new just did that and if they're having
problem that might mean that I missed
something so I really need to make sure
that installing git bash is
enough uh did anyone else see that
smooth ass effect yeah I I do that all
the time you just tested it kiss okay
well I'm sorry this video is going to be
uh about 90 minutes because we're doing
this tangent if you want to skip the
tangent you can do that um but I feel
like this is important I want to make
sure to get this down um so culus were
you able were you were you able to run
this setup I I'm not suggesting people
run the setup right away by the way uh I
know somebody jumped ahead and did that
um and uh by the way you do have to run
do setup if you're going to do that but
the rest I want to take you through how
you can do this without running the
global setup and you can go through each
individual setup script as opposed to
running the massive one maybe you
shouldn't even mention it uh it's not in
the book right in the book I don't say
hey if you want to skip the whole thing
just do setup and go be done um I don't
say that because because I would I'd
rather you go through it so but if but
for those somebody who did do that I
want to make sure it actually still
works um so see how it's replacing
another thing to note on G bash um is
some as a solid get sometimes in the
past may have uh the system of global
config would override expected Behavior
yes yes that's right that's what that's
exactly what I'm saying
if you if you know what you're doing and
you've already installed it and um then
you know that's that's the thing so so
you know that's that's this is one of
those cases where if I was individually
mentoring you we would figure out how
much you knew and how much you had done
but the book assumes you know nothing
and you haven't put anything on your
system okay if that if that if that is
does not describe you then we have to
deal with that each case individually
okay so next let's go down um so we've
got all this here so you CD into the do
files directory like we did you can LS
the directories in there look at all
that stuff we talked about that you can
set up get bash okay so now we're going
to proceed with setting up each of the
core tool configuration files
individually now as I said when you run
dogit bash or setup it does all of this
automatically so in the future if you
wanted to do that you could do that and
you probably will want to alter that and
add your own setups and config to there
uh if if you don't want to have to deal
with the individual configuration so but
we are going to go proceed with with
talking about what these things are and
we're going to look at them and we are
we are 47 minutes in so we got another
20 minutes or so so I think we're doing
good on time all right so the bachor C
file is a Hidden Gem in a world of shell
scripting terminal Wizardry you'll find
it in your home directory and um so let
me show you mine just to give you a
sense of somebody who's who's got one
already and um you show you what you're
going to get um so mine is uh well let's
actually not let's let's let's do what
you would do so you can do more or less
I'm going to do more I'm going to say
bash SL bashrc now notice that this does
not have a dot in front of it that's
because it's in your dot files and um
when we go back to the book here um it
says the bash or C is a hidden gemm this
is where your configuration goes this is
what sets up your aliases it's it's
where it's it's basically all of your
your customizations and everything it's
a big piece of your toolkit and um
having having a good bashrc file as your
starting thing is probably one of the
most important things you can do as a
beginner on the terminal um just because
there are so many little things that you
just won't remember and I do want to put
a note here that you know in the begin
boost
before very wrongly I used to teach you
how to code in Bash just so you could
understand your bash RC
pile that was stupid I mean really that
was stupid right because I was so into
having you understand everything I was
like okay we're going to drop everything
now and we're going to learn how to code
in bash so that you can read every line
of the bash RC and understand what's
going on we are not doing that in this
book this book is just trust me but go
look at it and if you want to come back
bash is a great programming language to
learn should it be your first
programming language probably not and in
the that boost last year's boost we
tried to learn bash is the first
language huge mistake huge
mistake I I love bash I absolutely
dearly love bash every time you write a
command everybody just in case you're
wondering every time you do anything on
the command line you are writing a line
of bash code which is really cool so
you're already coding just by typing
commands including that clone repo one
you wrote you wrote a line of bash code
code because the shell and I talk about
this later but the shell is an
interactive running program it's called
the shell it's a program that's running
it gives us our terminal it gives us our
command line it gives us specifically
our command line and it takes in a
command runs it and then prints out the
result and then loops around it's called
a repple yeah read evaluate print Loop
read evaluate print Loop read evaluate
print Loop this it's called a repple
that's what a command line is right
that's the interface and and Bash is one
of many shells you'll hear about bash
and zshell and Powers shell and there's
all kinds of command interactive command
line shells and Bash is a really good
one bash is probably the biggest one it
is a language itself uh and if you want
to learn bash exhaustively uh terminal
velocity I'm going to put you off on
that but we are going to learn
everything about bash uh how to set up
your own tab completion everything we're
going to learn about bash in terminal
velocity because learning how to code in
bash makes you extremely powerful you
can write crazy crazy powerful things
right from the command line and I'm just
going to show you one so you can write
and but not only can you write from the
command line you can integrate them into
your code so you can write you know 4 I
in I don't know one to 20 uh do Echo I
uh uh done right so let's say you wanted
to give yourself a whole bunch of line
numbers right you're like wouldn't it be
cool if I could put that in my in my
when I'm writing notes or something so
notes. MD so I'm going to write that and
now I'm going to say bang bang I can
actually write shell coat in my Vim cod
we're going to learn all of this in
terminal velocity so I'm just giving you
a taste so you're going to say 4 I in
one this is just to give you a taste and
keep you inticed because it's just so
freaking cool you're like wait you're
you're writing Shell Code and and and
markdown file why are you doing that for
that's crazy yeah hear me out so we're
going to do one right thing and then we
can say done all right so there's some
shell cut I watch bang bang we're going
to learn this we're going to learn this
in vim and then we're going to send this
command to bash and it's going to
replace that line of code in this text
file with the output boom here we go how
about that now watch um relative links
should also be observed um in bash
scripting relative links should always
be
observed relative links
I mean yes I
suppose it depends I mean are you
talking about dot slash I think you're
kind of get getting ahead okay watch
this what what happens if I want to turn
this into markdown I can send the whole
thing to a program that converts it into
HTML and it makes it into website okay
so again this is all by using bash is
your most powerful tool in terms of
editing things uh it's you're going to
be your dot files are going to be filled
with little bash Scripts uh and
everything so so please please um hang
tight on that but just understand that
that you know it's going to be a big
part of your life come back to bash in
termal velocity if you really want to
master it um and I strongly suggest you
do even if you decide to be a Zell or
fish person you're going to be better
off learning bash as a scripting
language because of the power and I'll
justify that statement in termal
velocity when we get to there um it bash
is definitely not for beginners no and
so there we go bash is a language when
you put those lines you've been putting
you know into a file you write a script
so a script is a runnable file and
executable that is a bunch of commands
one line after the other bash is serious
there's a lot of stuff to do there uh
okay when you did the ls you saw the
bash there he said okay so it's going to
put it in your home directory as bash RC
less is more we talked about what less
is already hey man we talked about what
man is uh check the setup script so
let's actually go look at what the setup
scrip for back RC is going to do let's
go look at that what that's going to do
so so uh so we already kind of did it
but let's actually do this this way so
let's CD into bash all right and you can
see now I'm in The Bash directory and
you can LS and you can see that there
are a bunch of files in here right and
okay so yeah and then let's go ahead and
we're going to look at this you can just
more or less but you can do more setup
and it will show you the whole thing so
there it is there is our our Command and
you don't need to know what it's going
to do what it does but I'm going to tell
you anyway what it does is it
replaces uh this this TIY means home
directory that's where you every time
you log in that's your home and you can
you know anytime you see a tilty that's
what that means by the way to get back
home at any time just do CD enter it
will take you home right let people do
CD tiled you don't have to do that it's
waste of time CD enter will take you
home all right and then you can go back
into dot let's go LS PWD you see where
we are LS and practices and then we're
going to CD back into M case. two
because I already have a one so and then
we look in here now we're going to CD
into bash and now we're in bash again
and we can actually more set up and see
the script and we see the lsf that says
Force the creation of a symbolic link so
um I'm using I'm using Western right now
but we're going to install it so what
this is these what this script is this
setup script is doing is it's it's
replacing if it exists The Bash RC the
input RC and the dur colors file in your
home directory with a link that points
to this one okay now now that we've seen
it now you can run it right so let's
just run this one let's just run this
one so in order to run if I were to type
setup right here it would not run it or
if it didn't run it it would be the
wrong one let's actually see which setup
type type setup it's like you can't find
setup right so we're going to run this
setup thing right here so to run this
see how it's red by the way ls- L you
see that look it shows you you can see
how the X's yeah that's where rwx Rob
comes from RBX and RBX robit where it
comes from read write and execute that
means it can be run it's a script so
it's red that's why it's that color that
means it can be run the problem is is
it's in a weird place and my command
line doesn't know about it it's not in
the path which we'll talk about later so
now you do/ setup and you hit enter and
that is going to do some stuff it's
going to tell you what it did and now we
can actually check to see what it did
okay and this is where things get really
interesting right so we can do this we
can say ls- l and let's do um
ti.
bashrc and now that says hey I want to
look at the file the long form of the
file that's at that location and you can
see right here that this is created
what's called a symbolic link uh that's
what the L stands for and uh there's
also something called hard links but
we're not going to talk about it we'll
talk about that in termal velocity but
this this says that and for all intents
and purposes that file is this file
right and and and you're going to hear
you're going to hear a lot of people who
are going to tell you to not use
symbolic link I'm telling you it's the
easiest because that way you can make
changes if I make changes to the bash or
CP let me show you just for
demonstration purposes don't do this but
if if I wanted to change anywh on the
system if I wanted to change bash RC and
I wanted to say uh you know Echo hello
there uh good day and now every time my
Bach RC runs it gives me a greeting
right let's say I want to do something
like that now watch now it's not going
to work so to get the new changes to
your bachor C have to use another
command EXA bash DL it stands for login
shell if you want to you can do D- login
instead if it's easier for you to
remember uh but you can do dashell and
what this does is that reruns the
configuration file starts a new bash and
you can see as it started a new bash it
printed out my thing and it has a change
to it but this is what I'm trying to
show you you know I changed the file you
don't know how to do that yet but I
changed the file at this location right
in my home directory and what I want to
show you is that it also changed the
file here so the file that was here was
also changed you see that that's because
it's a symbolic link and that is the
nature of symbolic links they are
effectively a file in two different
places even though it's the same file
now there is one very important thing I
have to tell you here about Windows
Windows does not have symbolic links
so as a beginner you don't care but you
need to know I'm going to say it anyway
when you're on a beginner when when you
run this script on git bash for Windows
it will not create a symbolic link it
will create a copy so then you have two
copies and the only thing you need to
know about that is that those two are
different for the sake of this book that
whole thing where I changed the thing
does not apply to Windows and this is
why in terminal velocity we don't use G
bash anymore we use something more
powerful all right but I'm just going to
say it to you right now because I don't
want there's going to be at least one
person that's going to say what but it
doesn't do symbolic links on Windows
there's no such thing the only reason
we're using get bash is because we want
to get past that stuff but I'm kind of
Miss Even mentioning it because now
people are going to miss out and they're
like why can't I use something else
instead right now just stay with me I'm
sorry I said
it okay so uh yeah so it's
like anyway
um anyway I want you to just know that
that that's the thing and um so now what
now you should be able you have a
different bashor C so after you ran SL
setup everybody the next thing to do is
is is do it now now if you you should
have seen a change you should have seen
a change let me let me show I'm going to
do the same thing on Windows because
Windows is a fresh system okay so so in
uh in well let me think here so all
right so I'm I'm gonna just let me let
me don't do this don't do this don't do
this I'm doing this to get ready to show
you something new okay so I'm going back
to to as if I I'm pretending like I
never had it before
all right um so I think it's still there
somehow I think it's still
there I don't know nope it's not
okay let me try something else I'm going
to start up again all right here we go
bash get
bash all right so here's the here's the
Baseline get bash prompt
okay um
and all right so let's let's do the same
thing we just did so CD into was it
dot files
2 and I I mean you should you should
have the latest here but I'm just want
to make sure I have the latest all right
so then we do CD into
bash right and then we do slash setup
there it doesn't do symbolic links in
Windows it
doesn't watch I'll show you-
l. bash
RC see that's not a symbolic
link I did an ln- SF and it does not
great it it creates a copy and it does
not put an L here so as far as bash is
concerned it's not a symbolic link it's
a copy now let's do let's the exec bash
DL and get a new shell and then you'll
get the the happier uh prompt so what do
you do there what do we do let's recap
what we did um because it's an hour in
and we're going to do the other
configurations next I'm going to go
ahead and end here so so what what have
we accomplished we we got you know the
dot files downloaded we went in there we
understood how to look around at some
different things and then we actually
ran the setup script for bash only that
ran that setup bash and that gave us a
new prompt and then we were able to log
in and now we actually have a lot of
other things that it's done uh but I I
don't want to overwhelm you right now
but it's it's it's enabled a bunch of
things not to mention that's the least
of which is you know a prettier command
line uh interface right there are many
many other things that have been enabled
here uh one of them is a command called
path which we're going to use later that
that's much easier to to see about your
path and thing so we're going to do
clear to clear the screen and on that
note we're going to go ahead uh we're
not we're not going to do that um so
please don't confuse people willfulness
we're talking to beginners here and this
this is is in the book uh so we have a
lot of absolute beginners here uh we are
not going to try to do extra stuff here
um somebody in the chat is trying to
tell them that symbolic links don't work
on Windows and I'm telling you they
don't not out of the box anyway so uh
yeah no no we're not we're not doing
that that's that's not a thing the the
Ln command is the one we want the
beginner to learn not some random
esoteric Windows command so uh stay with
me okay okay so if if you're a beginner
and you're just watching this I'm going
to go ahead and wrap up the video now
today um and what should you do let's
just recap so you know where you are um
this this is the hard part about doing
this live is everybody wants to help and
and I'm speaking to you who's watching
it as the beginner I'm speaking to you
right now you can tell all the people
who think they know what they're talking
about to just be quiet for a bit and
that if that includes me fine but right
now you're here to trust me that try to
find the simplest way to get through it
okay and the simplest way to get through
it is is to tell everybody to shut up
and to stick with the simplest possible
way I promise you you will understand
all of those Advanced things that
they're trying to tell you to do and
trying to do this and that and the line
ending problem and how to make a Sim
link and hard link what's the difference
and and you know all those things and
whether you should use git bash or
Windows or wsl2 and all these things
right now just just turn it off turn off
all that noise and stay with me as we go
through the rest of these configurations
okay so today's configuration the one
that we're ending with is Bash RC you
now have bash installed it's running you
know what it is in general and you're
ready to move on so the next steps are
going to be um we're going to go we we
got our first dot files created we set
up bash with bash RC and now we're going
to set up a really fancy terminal so
stay tuned and you can do cool things
like the sunrise app yeah you can do all
sorts of fun things uh later um when we
when we get on to the the next thing
after this um but that's not here yet
we're not quite there yet just yet so
we'll see you in the next video go take
a break everybody